Indiana University Chemistry Library records, 1855-2011 C564
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Chemistry Library records
1855-2011
1979-2002
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Chemistry Library
C564
3.6 cubic feet 4 boxes
With a history dating back to 1895, the Chemistry library was initially housed in Wylie Hall, however with the completion of the Chemistry building in the 1930s it relocated and remains in that location to this day. The collection consists primarily of administrative files such as handbook, notes and memos.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The core collection of the original Chemistry Library was donated by Dr. Robert Edward Lyons around 1895. Most of those early works are still in the book collection with his book plates on them. From 1895-1931, the Chemistry Library was housed in a room in Wylie Hall. It was moved to the ground floor of the new Chemistry Building in the early 1930s. The library was extensively remodeled and enlarged around 1965, and the present quarters were occupied during the remodeling and expansion of the Chemistry Building in the early 1990s.
The Chemistry Library has long been an early adopter of new information technology. It was the first unit on campus to have a photocopy machine and the first to have a CD-ROM player. An innovative current awareness service based on the Chemical Abstracts tapes was offered for a number of years during the 1970s, initially through ARAC (the Aerospace Research Applications Center), then through the Chemical Information Center (CIC). Housed in the library, the CIC was the first unit on campus, and indeed in the entire state of Indiana, to offer online searching of remote databases through the Dialog and Orbit systems. Miriam Bonham, wife of Emeritus Professor Russell A. Bonham, was the expert searcher who initially provided the service. A complete microfilming unit was part of the CIC operations for many years, providing compact archival storage for laboratory notebooks and Molecular Structure Center reports.
In 1985, the Chemistry Library was one of the first in the world to offer the Chemical Abstracts Service Academic Program that permits low-cost searching of the CAS ONLINE files. For 10 years, this service was offered at no cost to the user. CAS ONLINE was replaced at IUB by SciFinder Scholar in the mid-1990s. Since July 2000, SciFinder Scholar has been available at all IU campuses 24 hours/day with full substructure searching. In combination with current subscriptions to all of the American Chemical Society journal Web editions and electronic versions of other chemistry journals (including backfiles of most of them), the SciFinder Scholar databases provide unparalleled access to the major primary and secondary sources in chemistry. Another resource that has been available to IU researchers at all campuses since its inception is the CrossFire system that includes both the Beilstein Handbook of Organic Chemistry and the Gmelin Handbook of Inorganic and Organometallic Chemistry. The Cambridge Structural Database is also provided by the Chemistry Library.
The Chemistry Library remains open on Bloomington's campus and is located in the Chemistry Building.
Arrangement
Records are organized into two series, Administrative files and Subject files. Within both series, files are organized alphabetically by folder heading.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Indiana University Chemistry Library span the years 1855-2011; the bulk of the collection is concentrated in the years from 1979-2002. Records are organized into two series, Administrative files and Subject files. Within both series, files are organized alphabetically by folder heading.
Contained within the Administrative files are such subjects as the ongoing maintenance of the library's journals and serials, including correspondence and memos on renewals and cancellations. Represented within this topic are memos, e-mails, letter correspondence, and printed lists of journals collected by the Chemistry Library. In addition, there are reports reflecting the then-current status of library holdings and issues. Other topics include past upgrades and remodeling of the library facilities, including proposed expansions, materials measurements, floor plans, remodeling drawings, and cost estimates. These topics are represented in part through correspondence, internal memos, e-mail, and various notes. Another subject within the series concerns materials for the Chemical Information Center (CIC), an information clearinghouse maintained by the Chemistry Library at that time. Included are annual reports on the status of the CIC and materials describing the history of the Center. Also included in the series are general annual library reports for the Chemistry Library, materials concerning other chemistry information centers affiliated with Indiana University, and correspondence/ memos on the status and changes to the facilities at the Chemistry Library. There are also posters explaining how to use to the Clearinghouse for Chemical Information Instructional Materials (CCIIM). Finally, the series includes materials relating to the history of the Chemistry Library, including photographs, handbooks, notes, memos, and chronologies of the library's past development.
The next series, Subject files, features a variety of materials relating to the general development of chemistry as a science and as a profession. Many of the files are sourced from the historical surveys of chemistry taught through the department in the past. Included in the series are journal and magazine clippings, submitted student reports, handwritten notecards, memos, course syllabi, copies of exams, article reprints, and copies of original source documents.
Photographs Pulled
Approximately two dozen photographs depicting the Chemistry Library and staff functions have been pulled from the collection and are now housed with the Archives Photo collection.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory.
Archived web sites for the Library may be included in Archive-It.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2014/061
Chemical libraries--Collection development--Indiana--Bloomington--History--Sources.; Chemical libraries--Information technology--Indiana--Bloomington--History--Sources.; Indiana University, Bloomington. Chemistry Library -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Chemistry Library -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Chemistry Library -- Administration -- History -- Sources
- Administrative files, 1931-2011 (Box 1)
  - ACS/SLA Clearinghouse for Chemical Information Instructional Materials, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports—Chemistry Library, 1943-1993 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Library Faculty Handbook, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Branch Library Serials Management System, 1987-1997 (Box 1)
  - Cancellations (Box 1)
    - 1978-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
  - Chemical Data Services (Box 1)
    - 1982-1998 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Articles, 1959-1999 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Journal Studies, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Design of Facility, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Holdings, 1985-1996 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Newsletter, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Procedures, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Research Information, 2003-2011 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Library Search Manual, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Meetings and Information, 1950-1991 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Resource Center, 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - CIC: History, 1976-2000 (Box 1)
  - CIC Annual Report: Master, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
  - Citation Studies (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Citation Studies with Ranking, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Clearinghouse for Chemical Information Instructional Materials, 1994-1998 (Box 1)
    General
    (See Box 4)
  - Collection Development Studies & Reports, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
  - Computer Classroom 006, 1986-1994 (Box 1)
  - Core Chemistry Journals, 1978-1988 (Box 1)
  - Core Journals Project, 1987-1994 (Box 2)
  - Handbook—Chemistry Library, 1977-1992 (Box 2)
  - History of the Chemistry Library, 1931-2000 (Box 2)
  - Index Request, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Index to Standard Interest Profiles, 1987-1994 (Box 2)
  - Index to SIPs in S&T, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Index to Standard Interest Profiles in Science and Technology, 1988 (Box 2)
  - IU Libraries Reports, 2003-2009 (Box 2)
  - Journal Cancellations, Spring 1996; 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Library Staff Annual Review, 1980-2002 (Box 2)
  - NCIP Verification Project, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Potential Cancellations, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - Processing Manual, 1983-1999 (Box 2)
  - Science Citation Index, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
  - Science Lib's Reports, 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Science Libraries Document Delivery Project, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Serials Control Manual, 1990-1998 (Box 2)
  - Serials Study (Box 2)
    - CA "List of 1000 Journals": Titles at IUB, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Chemistry Faculty Citation Studies, 1976-1989 (Box 2)
    - IN-ND-PU (Based on Journal Citation Reports), 1984-1990 (Box 2)
    - RLG, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - SIP (Box 2)
    - Brochures, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Letters, 1978-1994 (Box 2)
  - Mailing List for Index, 1987 (Box 2)
  - The Oryx Press, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Scientific Publications of the Department of Chemistry, 1979-1991 (Box 2)
  - Space Plans Correspondence, etc., 1987-1997 (Box 2)
  - Standby Order for Index, 1979-1998 (Box 2)
  - Tri-Society Symposium, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Work Area/Offices, 1991 (Box 2)
- Subject files, 1855-1984 (Box 3)
  - 19th Century Chemistry, circa 1976 (Box 3)
  - Agricola, Ercker, Paracelsus, Van Helmont, J. Becker, 1962-1978 (Box 3)
  - Alchemy and Chemistry Prior to 1500, 1960-1984 (Box 3)
  - Atomic Molecular Theory (Dalton, Higgins), circa 1973-1986 (Box 3)
  - Avogadro, Proust, Berthollet, Cannizzato, Gay-Lussac, 1956-1978 (Box 3)
  - Biography—Hildebrand, 1962-1980 (Box 3)
  - Boyle, R.—Newton, I., F. Bacon, Lemery, Lomonosov, 17th Cent., circa 1960-1984 (Box 3)
  - C403, Scientific Societies, Royal Society of London and Others, 1956-1978 (Box 3)
  - C404 (Box 3)
    - Analytical Chemisty, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Chemical Industry, 1968-1978 (Box 3)
    - Handouts, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Handout Original, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    - Examinations, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    - Handouts—Report topics, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
    - Physical Chemistry, Maturity, 20th Cent., circa 1962-1982 (Box 3)
    - Physical Chemistry Origins, 19th Cent. Ostwald, Gibbs, Arrhenius, undated (Box 3)
  - Congress at Karlsruhe, undated (Box 3)
  - Davy, Volta, Berzelius, Count Rumford, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Faraday, 1855-1967 (Box 3)
  - History, Biological Chemistry, Nutrition, undated (Box 3)
  - History of Chemistry (Box 3)
    - 1956-1978 (Box 3)
    - C-404, 1959-1979 (Box 3)
    - Introduction, General, 1953-1979 (Box 3)
    - J. Black—Originals—Copies, 1954-1964 (Box 3)
    - Reference Files (Box 3)
      - 1950-1989 (Box 3)
      - 1951-1995 (Box 3)
      - 1992-1996 (Box 3)
      - 1993-1998 (Box 3)
      - 1994-1999 (Box 3)
      - 1995-1998 (Box 3)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Inorganic Chemistry, Fundamental Develops, Weeks, Elements (Ramsey, Mellor), 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - Lavoisier, R., M. Lavoisier, 1954-1963 (Box 3)
  - Laurent, Gerhardt, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Medicinal Chemistry, 1896-1989 (Box 3)
  - Organic Chemistry (Box 3)
    - (Liebig, Wohler, Dumas, Chevreul), 1949-1983 (Box 3)
    - Consolidation, Growth, 1974-1986 (Box 3)
    - Remsen, Grignard, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Periodic Table, (Mendeleev), 1891-1987 (Box 3)
  - Phlogiston Theory (J. Priestley, H. Cavendish, C. Scheele, B. Franklin), 1956-1983 (Box 3)
  - Royal Institution, 1937-1976 (Box 3)
  - Useful Quotes for Introduction, undated (Box 3)
  - Wohler and Vitalism, 1956-1959 (Box 3)
- Oversized Materials (Box 4)